Franklin M. Loew Papers MS278
Tufts Archival Research Center
Franklin M. Loew Papers
circa 1808 -- 2002
1961 -- 2002
Tufts Archival Research Center
Loew, Franklin M.
MS278
21 Linear Feet 21 record cartons
This collection contains materials from the life and career of Dr. Franklin M. Loew, who served as Dean of the Tufts School of Veterinary Medicine from 1982-1995 in addition to holding positions at several other universities. Materials include correspondence, administrative records, research and reference materials, newpaper clippings, and writings by Loew, as well as audiovisual materials related to veterinary medicine and teaching.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in received order.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Franklin M. Loew (1939-2003) served as Dean of the Tufts School of Veterinary Medicine from 1982-1995. Loew was born in Syracuse, New York in 1939. He received his bachelor's degree in 1961, and his doctorate in veterinary medicine in 1965, from Cornell University. He also completed a doctorate in nutrition from the University of Saskatchewan in Canada, where he was then appointed Professor of Physiology and the Director of the Resource Program in Toxicology at the university's Animal Resources Center. He would hold this position from 1967-1977, before accepting the position of Director of the Department of Comparative Medicine at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, where he would serve from 1977-1982. From 1982-1995, Dr. Loew was the Dean of the Tufts School of Veterinary medicine. During his tenure at Tufts, he greatly increased the profile of the Veterinary School, developing specialties in biotechnology, equine sports medicine, wildlife medicine, and veterinary ethics. Loew then left Tufts to become the Dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Cornell University, where he stayed from 1995-1997, before becoming the CEO of Medical Foods Inc. in 1997. Dr. Loew then served as the eighth President of Becker College from 1998 until his death in 2003.
In the 1970s, Loew was a member of the award-winning research team behind the development and commercialization of canola oil. In addition to numerous scientific articles and op-ed pieces, Loew was also the author of "Vet in the Saddle: John L. Poett, First Veterinary Surgeon in the North West Mounted Police," published in 1978. He was also elected a member of the American Antiquarian Society in 1990 and held several other non-profit boards of trustees positions throughout his career. Dr. Loew was married twice, first to Mary Moffatt Loew, and later to Deborah Digges, Professor of English at Tufts from 1986-2009. He had two sons, Timothy and Andrew Loew, as well as two stepsons, Charles and Stephen Digges. Franklin Loew died in April 2003. The Franklin M. Loew Veterinary Education Center at the Tufts School of Veterinary Medicine's Grafton campus was dedicated in 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials from the life and career of Dr. Franklin M. Loew, Dean of the Tufts School of Veterinary Medicine from 1982-1995. Included are materials from Dr. Loew's various academic and leadership positions, including Professor at the University of Saskatchewan from 1967-1977, Director of the Department of Comparative Medicine at Johns Hopkins School of Medicine from 1977-1982, Dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine at Cornell University from 1995-1997, CEO of Medical Foods Inc. from 1997-1998, and President of Becker College from 1998-2003.
Record types include correspondence, administrative records, research and reference materials, newpaper clippings, and writings by Loew, as well as VHS and cassette tape recordings related to veterinary medicine, slides of research materials, floppy disks, and photographic prints. Topics discussed include, but are not limited to, veterinary medicine generally and its historical development, ethical treatment of animal research subjects, nutritional research, higher education administration, and collaborative research with both American and international colleagues.
Custodial History
This collection was transferred to the Archives by John Bourgeois, Library Manager for the Webster Family Library at the Cummings School of Veterinary Medicine at Tufts University.
Appraisal
Family and personal photographs were removed from the collection.
Veterinary medicine -- Study and teaching; Faculty papers
- Personal and professional files, 1967 -- 2001; MS278.000001 (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  75 years from date of creation.
  Scope and Contents
  This box contains personal and professional files related to Dr. Loew's employment at various univerisities, publishing, veterinary accreditation, personal research, and philanthropic service.
- Professional files, 1922 -- 2002; MS278.000002 (Box 2)
  This box contains appointment books for the years 1977-1990, Tufts materials, and subject files.
- Professional subject files, 1964 -- 1997; MS278.000003 (Box 3)
  This box contains administrative materials related to Tufts, including presidential search and Board of Trustees materials. Also subject files related to Rapeseed Oil, Selenium, and work with other Universities.
- Professional subject files, 1966 -- 1994; MS278.000004 (Box 4)
  This box contains correspondence with various colleagues, files related to Dr. Loew's work in Canada, and research subject files.
- Professional subject files, 1961 -- 1994; MS278.000005 (Box 5)
  This box contains correspondence and Cornell materials, as well as international research files related to Cuba, East Germany and Canada.
- Professional subject files, 1938 -- 2000; MS278.000006 (Box 6)
  This box contains personal files, professional correspondence, publications and speeches by Dr. Loew.
- Professional subject files, 1894 -- 2001; MS278.000007 (Box 7)
  This box contains personal and professional correspondence, research files and reports related to student recruitment to veterinary programs, publications, reference files and notes, and materials related to Becker College. Also included is a drawing of Dr. Loew signed by Eric Carle.
- Professional subject files, 1978 -- 2001; MS278.000008 (Box 8)
  This box contains personal files, professional correspondence, research and reference files, reports, and publishing files.
- Professional subject files, 1891 -- 2001; MS278.000009 (Box 9)
  Open for research.
  This box contains research and reference files, newspaper clippings, and reprints of articles by Dr. Loew.
- Professional subject files, 1989 -- 2001; MS278.000010 (Box 10)
  This box contains research and reference files, some related to "Vet in the Saddle: John L. Poett, First Veterinary Surgeon Of The North West Mounted Police." Also includes personal and professional correspondence.
- Professional subject files, 1967 -- 1995; MS278.000011 (Box 11)
  This box contains personal and professional correspondence, including correspondence with Jane Goodall. Also files related to research and work with Cornell, Johns Hopkins, M.I.T, and the Institute of Medicine.
- Professional subject files, 1991 -- 2002; MS278.000012 (Box 12)
  This box contains correspondence, reference files, and materials related to Ross University.
- Professional subject files, 1808 -- 2001; MS278.000013 (Box 13)
  This box contains personal and professional correspondence, including correspondence with the family of John L. Poett. Also includes research materials on various topics, including women in the veterinary profession, and publications.
- Writings and clippings, 1967 -- 1985; MS278.000014 (Box 14)
  This box contains binders of writings and newspaper clippings related to the work of Dr. Loew.
- Writings and clippings, 1981 -- 1986; MS278.000015 (Box 15)
- Speeches, writings, and clippings, 1987 -- 1990; MS278.000016 (Box 16)
  This box contains binders of speeches, writings, and newspaper clippings related to the work of Dr. Loew.
- Speeches, writings, and clippings, 1989 -- 1993; MS278.000017 (Box 17)
- Writings and clippings, 1991 -- 1993; MS278.000018 (Box 18)
- Speeches, writings, and clippings, 1994; MS278.000019 (Box 19)
- Speeches, writings, and clippings, 1992 -- 1995; MS278.000020 (Box 20)
- Audiovisual materials, circa 1969 -- 1993; MS278.000021 (Box 21)
  This box contains audiovisual materials related to the career of Dr. Loew. Formats include VHS, U-Matic, reels, slides, and photographic prints.
  - Dr. Francisco Gonzalez Mencio, no. 1 and no. 2, MS278.000022; 2 Digital Object(s) 2 3.5 inch floppy disks (Box Shared Digital Media 1)